<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The interest of England in the Irish transplantation, stated wherein is held forth (to all concerned in Irelands good settlement) the benefits the Irish transplantation will bring to each of them in particular, and to the Common-wealth in general, being chiefly intended as an answer to a scandalous, seditious pamphlet, entituled, The great case of transplantation in Ireland discussed. Composed and published at the request of several persons in eminent place in Ireland, to the end all who desire it, might have a true account of the proceedings that have been there in the business of transplantation, both as to the rise, progress, and end thereof. By a faithfull servant of the Common-wealth, Richard Laurence.</title>
            <author>Lawrence, Richard, d. 1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74937</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L678</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E829_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R179375</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899670</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899670</idno>
            <idno type="VID">132301</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74937)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132301)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2430:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The interest of England in the Irish transplantation, stated wherein is held forth (to all concerned in Irelands good settlement) the benefits the Irish transplantation will bring to each of them in particular, and to the Common-wealth in general, being chiefly intended as an answer to a scandalous, seditious pamphlet, entituled, The great case of transplantation in Ireland discussed. Composed and published at the request of several persons in eminent place in Ireland, to the end all who desire it, might have a true account of the proceedings that have been there in the business of transplantation, both as to the rise, progress, and end thereof. By a faithfull servant of the Common-wealth, Richard Laurence.</title>
                  <author>Lawrence, Richard, d. 1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Henry Hills, and are to be sold at the sign of Sir John Oldcastle near Py-coruer [sic],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MCDLV. [1455, i.e. 1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Gookin, Vincent.  Great case of transplantation in Ireland discussed.</note>
                  <note>The words "The great case .. discussed." are enclosed in square brackets on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "1654 March. 9"; V in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Identified as Wing L678, reel 2430, of the UMI microfilm set "Early English books 1641-1700".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Royal College of Physicians Library, London.</note>
                  <note>Identified by ESTC as Wing (CD-ROM, 1996) L677.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gookin, Vincent, 1616?-1659. --  Great case of transplantation in Ireland discussed --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Economic conditions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Commerce --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Politics and government --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:132301:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE INTEREST OF ENGLAND IN THE IRISH Tranſplantation, ſtated: Wherein is held forth (to all concerned in <hi>Irelands</hi> good ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) the benefits the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Tranſplantation will bring to each of them in particular, and to the Common-wealth in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, being chiefly intended as an Anſwer to a ſcandalous, ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Pamphlet, entituled, [<hi>The great Caſe of Transplanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in</hi> Ireland <hi>diſcuſſed.</hi>] Compoſed and publiſhed at the requeſt of ſeveral perſons in eminent place in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to the end all who deſire it, might have a true Account of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings that have been there in the buſineſs of Tranſplanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, both as to the riſe, progreſs, and end thereof.</p>
            <p>By a faithfull Servant of the Common-wealth, <hi>Richard Laurence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Sign of Sir <hi>John Oldcastle</hi> near <hi>Py-corner.</hi> MCDLV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:132301:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:132301:2"/>
            <head>THE INTEREST OF ENGLAND IN THE IRISH Tranſplantation.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O avoid prolixity, and diverting the judgment of the Reader, by impertinencies, from the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of ſo weighty a buſineſs, I ſhall decline the way of an orderly Anſwer to the ſeveral Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and Objections of the Diſcuſſor, as they ſtand in his Book, by which I ſhould have been neceſſitated to take notice of many impertinences as to this buſineſs in hand, beſides the many ſcrupulous expreſſions and ſcandalous reflections contained therein againſt Authority, whoſe contrary demeanour and actions are ſo publickly and well known to many thouſands of judicious, ſober perſons, both <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> in this Nation, that my teſtimony would be as needleſs in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their vindication, as the Diſcuſſors ſcandalous clamors are like to be ſucceſleſs, in the ſtain of their reputation: and therefore they ſeem more to convince the Reader of the Diſcuſſors ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:132301:3"/>
and weakneſs, than of the rationality of the thing therein pleaded for; wherefore I ſhall for brevities ſake confine my ſelf to a plain and true Account (ſo far as my memory and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſhall help me) of this buſineſs of Tranſplantation, in which I ſhall uſe this method, and ſpeak,</p>
            <p>Firſt, of the original Authority of this buſineſs of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantation, from whence it came.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the reaſons and grounds upon which it was under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken by the Parliament, as they are declared in the Act of Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement and Inſtructions for Tranſplantation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the proceedings that have been herein from time to time by the Authority of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in obſervance of the ſaid Act of Parliament and Inſtructions, wherein is to be minded their prudence and tenderneſs therein, contrary to thoſe in jurious inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations of ſeverity and cruelty ſuggeſted by the Diſcuſſor againſt them.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Is obſerved the great miſtake the Diſcuſſor grounds his whole diſcourſe upon, the clearing of which, of it ſelf might be a ſufficient Anſwer to the whole Book, all the Arguments within it being raiſed therefrom.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, ſeveral of the moſt ſwaying Reaſons, and Arguments, offered by the Diſcuſſor againſt the Work, examined and anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with ſome Arguments preſented to conſideration in oppoſition thereto.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the weakneſs and malice of the Diſcuſſor is much diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by his endeavours to lay the blame of the work of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantation (if it were blame worthy) orginally or chiefly upon the perſons in chief Authority in <hi>Ireland,</hi> Whereas they were but miniſterial and ſubordinate therein, onely putting the Orders and Inſtructions of Parliament in execution when received, ſo that had they or any ſubordinate to them there, been as much diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in the work, as the Diſcuſſor, yet it remained upon them as a duty ſo far as it was poſſible in their power to ſee the thing done.</p>
            <p>Then ſecondly, for the Reaſons which the Parliament grounds the work of Tranſplantation upon, as they are hinted and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for in the Act of Settlement, <hi>pag.</hi> 13, 17, 22. and mentioned in the Inſtructions <hi>pag.</hi> 1, <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. you may there obſerve, they are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:132301:3"/>
not upon that hand the Diſcuſſor would fix them, <hi>viz.</hi> to puniſh the <hi>Iriſh</hi> for Rebellion and Murther for the time paſt, as he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth, and ſpends his pains about from <hi>pag.</hi> 7, to the 15. but on the other hand, to preſerve the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſo to ſettle <hi>Ireland</hi> for the future, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt and People might not be liable to the like inhumane uſage and deſtruction for the time to come, which we have reaſon to believe) they judged they could not do without this work of Tranſplantation, which being the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of a Parliament (nay, of ſeveral Parliaments one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, approving and confirming each others Acts therein) and withall not a ſudden Act, admitting of a probability of ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize before they had well adviſed and weighed the thing (it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under conſideration above twelve Moneths, and they being the ſupreme legiſlative power of theſe three Nations) The conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of all which might have been ſufficient to have caution<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Diſcuſſor (though he be in his own conceit more able to judg of that work than they all) to have been more modeſt in his language, eſpecially in a buſineſs of that nature, that no particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons could propoſe ſelf-advantage thereby, and withall of that weight, that the ſettlement of a Nation depends upon it.</p>
            <p>But the Diſcuſſor (me thinks) ſeems to imply an Objection againſt this in <hi>page</hi> 27, <hi>&amp;</hi> 28. of his Book, that though the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Tranſplantation were the Reſult of the wiſdom of a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and though the Parliament might conſiſt of wiſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate men, that underſtood and weighed well what they did, yet (ſaith he) (to ſtop the wonder, how ſuch deſtructive Reſolutions could paſs or be let paſs from the hands of Authority all this time) conſider,</p>
            <p>Firſt, thoſe that were in <hi>England</hi> muſt ſee and hear by theis eys and ears that were in <hi>Ireland,</hi> who (as he ſaith) were ſtrangers to that Land, and could not at the firſt ſight underſtand the compleat intereſt thereof.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the face of things is much different in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and though then neceſſity might have made it fit to have tranſplanted, yet now the unfitneſs makes it not neceſſary.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, though then in their wiſdoms they gave out ſuch Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, yet in their goodneſs they did not think fit to execute them even till this time, as if they did wait a time to be gracious to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:132301:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:132301:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:132301:5"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:132301:5"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:132301:6"/>Theſe things are propoſed as a premoniſhment to ſtop won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, (ſaith the Diſcuſſor) But where doth this wonder lie? Is it in that we had no wiſer a Parliament that better underſtood what they did in matters of ſo great importance, or that ſo wiſe a man as the Diſcuſſor ſhould not be found out to take advice from? It is my opinion, If that Parliament which firſt contrived and agreed the buſineſs of Tranſplantation were now in being, they would be able to convince the Diſcuſſor, that the ignorance of the ſtate and conſtitution of <hi>Ireland,</hi> by better Arguments than I can uſe, is rather the ariſe of his Book, than the occaſion of their Act.</p>
            <p>And if any rebellious conſequence ſhould be the effect of his or the like Papers, in ſuch a nick of Settlement, I doubt not but God would enable that Authority yet in being, to let out that dramm of rebellious bloud, and cure that fit of ſullenneſs he ſpeaks of <hi>pag.</hi> 25. And to let him know what it is to inſtigate a People to rebell againſt the Authority over them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they did ſee and hear with others eys and ears, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe he doth not mean that (in the <hi>interim</hi>) they ſhut their own, and if not, but they conſidered of and weighed the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice they received from all hands; then the more they conſulted with, the more their Reſults ought to be valued; for in the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Counſellours there is ſafety.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thoſe whom they adviſed with were ſtrangers to</hi> Ireland.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe, they that deſired their adviſe did not take them to be ſo, for they ſhould not need to ſend over to <hi>Ireland</hi> (as he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth they did) for advice from ſuch as were ſtrangers there; they might have had many ſuch nearer hand. But by the way, you may obſerve the Diſcuſſor was not adviſed with, or at leaſt if they did take his advice, they did not like his counſel, which (I am aſſured) proceeded not from a neglect of ſerious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in the buſineſs, but rather that thoſe in Authority had not altogether ſo good an opinion of the Diſcuſſors judgment in matters of that weight as (it appears) himſelf hath. For I do know very many perſons both of intereſt and underſtanding of the ancient <hi>Engliſh</hi> Inhabitants in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that were adviſed with in this matter both at <hi>Westminster</hi> and in <hi>Ireland;</hi> beſides,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:132301:6"/>
thoſe whom he calls ſtrangers, (I hope) are not ſo much ſtrangers to the preſent conſtitution and ſtate of <hi>Ireland,</hi> but that they are able to give judgment, that the preſent intended Tranſplantation is as eſſential to the future peace and ſafety of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt there, as the ſtopping the Leak of a Ship is, to keep it from ſinking.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> (ſaith the Diſcuſſor in his ſecond Head) <hi>the face of things is much differed in</hi> Ireland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he doth not tell you of which hand, whether better or worſe, whether the <hi>Iriſh</hi> be grown ſo honeſt that there is no need of it, or whether ſo conſiderable and ſtubborn that there is no poſſibility to do it. But I do take his meaning to be of the later, from what he ſaith to that point <hi>pag.</hi> 25. which I ſhall further ſpeak to in its place, and ſhall onely give my aſſent to the truth of this one Aſſertion, as to the preſent ſtate of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that the face of things are altered there; for time was when ſuch Incendiaries durſt not have been ſo impudent in miſ-repreſenting the tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of things there, as the Diſcuſſor by his Lines, and ſome others of his Accomplices by their falſe Reports and miſ-repreſentations have done and daily do; but time will manifeſt what they aim at and drive towards, that have ſo imployed themſelves, to their ſhame, and the future caution (I hope) of any of our friends in <hi>England,</hi> that have been too apt to credit them. But I am loth to imitate the Diſcuſſor by impertinencies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> the third Argument the Diſcuſſor produceth by way of Apology in the behalf of Authority, to prevent our wondring at them, <hi>that they ſhould be ſo overſeen,</hi> as he ſaith <hi>they were here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, is to tell you, that what their wiſdoms thought fit to order, their goodneſs did not think fit to execute, as if</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they waited a time to be gracious to the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſumm of which, ſo farr as I can make it hang together, is this, that the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and the Authority under them in <hi>Ireland,</hi> hath been for near theſe two years ſpending their time, pains and treaſure, about the work of Tranſplantation, and running all thoſe difficulties and hazards that have attended the ſame, to no other end, but to bring the People of <hi>Ireland</hi> into more miſery, that they might have an oportunity to ſhew mercy to them; Truly if this have been their deſign, there be a great many more wonderers at them, beſides the Diſcuſſor. And I hope there
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:132301:7"/>
is not the ſimpleſt <hi>Iriſhman</hi> that is to remove in <hi>Connaught,</hi> who will have ſo little wit, as to believe it, they have had and may have cauſe to judg the Authority in <hi>Ireland</hi> more ſerious in their proceeding with them. But I ſuſpect the Gentleman was not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious upon this Head, for comparing this with the cloſe of his Book, modeſtly deſiring them to forbear what they cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, think he rather intended it as a reproach upon Authority, he judging (as I ſuppoſe by the way he takes) the beſt means to ſettle <hi>Ireland</hi> to be, by repreſenting the Authority there not onely oppreſſive but ridiculous, in regard that wiſdom, goodneſs and and graciouſneſs here, hinted to be in thoſe that ſit at the Helm (as he calls them) is much inconſiſtent with that cruelty, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and other miſgovernments, which in the reſt of his Book he labors to lay to their charge.</p>
            <p>Then thirdly, as to the proceedings that have been in <hi>Ireland</hi> upon the buſineſs of Tranſplantation, ſince the arrival of thoſe Authorities and Inſtructions from the Parliament and Council of State, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Upon the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>September,</hi> 1653. was a ſhort Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (annexed to the aforeſaid Inſtructions) publiſhed by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of Parliament then at <hi>Dublin,</hi> requiring their mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters under them to cauſe the ſame to be forthwith publiſhed in their ſeveral Precincts.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>October</hi> following they again publiſhed a large De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration grounded upon the aforeſaid Act of Parliament, and Inſtructions of the Council of State, with a further Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament confirming the ſame, wherein was not onely expreſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, That notice ſhould be taken thereof, and obedience gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thereunto, but divers further Rules and Inſtructions given to the ſeveral Miniſters under them, in each Precinct in <hi>Ireland,</hi> (and eſpecially in <hi>Connaught</hi>) for the more orderly carrying on the work, not onely as to the Intereſt of the Common-wealth, in reſpect of the Revenue, and ſafety of the Nation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But alſo for the better encouragement of the People to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted, both as to the ſecurity of their Corn in Ground, and what other ſubſtance they ſhould leave behinde them, from ſpoil and loſs, and alſo to their journying by the way, and accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations there; after which were ſeveral ſupplemental Papers
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:132301:7"/>
publiſhed both as to the backing of this firſt Declaration (ſo far as it did extend, which were onely to Proprietors and men in Arms) as alſo to eaſe it where it might ſeem to bear hard upon any of them, it being much upon the hearts of thoſe in chief Authority in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to extend their power to the utmoſt length of the Line, in a way of tenderneſs towards the People to be removed, though there might be ſome inconveniences hazarded upon the Common-wealths part thereby, ſo far have they been from cruelty or ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards the people upon this Account (as is charged upon them by the diſcuſſor) for though the Parliament (in their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions) included all perſons within any the qualifications in the Act of Settlement, yet they in their Declarations thereupon, confine it to Proprietors of Lands, and perſons who had been in actual Rebellion, or (to uſe their own words) that had contrived, adviſed, promoted, acted, or voluntarily aided, aſſiſted or abetted the Rebellion, Murthers, Maſſacres, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or have been in actual Armes in the ſaid Rebellion. And leſt any under thoſe qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations ſhould come to be ſufferers for want of diſtinction, they iſſued out Authority to ſeveral of the chief Officers of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and other perſons of reputation and ability, to receive Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from any perſons in thoſe Rules, who had ought to offer in their own behalfs, either as to deſert from the Common-wealth for particular Acts of favour or kindneſs ſhewn to <hi>Engliſh</hi> in their extremity, or any other ſervice or teſtimony of the heart, true affection to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt, that it might not go un-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, by which power many hundreds within the aforeſaid Rules gained licence to ſtay, ſome for altogether, and ſome for more or leſs time, as they did deſerve, and their condition re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; and in regard there were ſome perſons who had done par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſervice and good offices to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt or People, and yet not ſo much as might deſerve a total exemption, yet that a Cup of cold Water might not go unrequited, (given by the worſt of Enemies to the meaneſt friends) they obtained ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for conſiderable times, ſome more and ſome leſs, with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for a ſpecial recommendation to the Commiſſioners for the diſpoſing of Lands to the tranſplanted people in <hi>Connaught,</hi> to take ſpecial care of them, and their convenient accommodation and ſettlement, beſides a general proviſion made by the ſame
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:132301:8"/>
Commiſſion, for all aged, decrepid, ſickly perſons, that no ſuch (though they had been in Arms againſt us) might be put upon hard things. And after all this, the generality of them (who had nothing to ſay as to point of merit or diſability of body) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king complaint that they ſhould be great ſufferers in their Corn in Ground and other ſubſtance, if they were not permitted to look after their Harveſt upon the places whence they removed, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained licence for their wives and families to continue upon their Holdings till Harveſt were in; and after that upon a ſecond complaint (that they could not diſpoſe of their Corn in ſo ſhort a time as was ſet them, but to their great loſs) they obtained gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral licence untill <hi>December</hi> laſt; and ſince that again, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of the hardneſs of the Seaſon of the Year to travell, they have their Licences renewed untill <hi>March</hi> next. It would ſwell into a Volume to mention the particular perſons towards whom this tenderneſs hath been extended from time to time. But theſe things thus generally hinted as a brief Narrative of the proceedings in <hi>Ireland</hi> in the buſineſs of Tranſplantation, being admitted to be true, (and if not credited, there are ſome thouſands of the Natives of <hi>Ireland,</hi> beſides many hundreds im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the Common-wealths ſervice, can give their teſtimony thereto) From what ground do you judg the Diſcuſſor can charge the Authority of <hi>Ireland</hi> with ſuch mercileſneſs and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, as that Book ſpeaks of and implies? Nay, there are ſome others who fear the error will prove on the other hand in the exerciſe of too much lenity and enderneſs towards a People that are likely enough to ill requite it, and to take advantage thereby, to put the work upon more difficulties. But if that ſhould be the fruit of the Diſcuſſors great affection to them, I doubt not (through Gods aſſiſtance) but in the end they would have as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle cauſe to reward him for his ſervice, as they have their Prieſts for ſtirring them up to the laſt Rebellion; however, they that have hitherto been exerciſed towards them with ſo much tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and compaſſion, aiming ſingly therein at their good, if they ſhould meet with that requital from them or any of them, I hope would with the more comfort and grounded reſolution be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged in the diſcharge of their duties on the other hand; and if any on the contrary hand ſhould take upon them to blame the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:132301:8"/>
proceedings of Authority herein, there's ſufficient reaſon to be ſhewn on that hand to juſtifie the prudent and tender proceedings that have been in this matter; but that would be here impertinent.</p>
            <p>And fourthly, as to the work of Tranſplantation it ſelf, though it lies not upon the Authority there to ſhew any farther reaſon for what they do therein, than what hath been before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, <hi>viz.</hi> the diſcharge of their duty, in putting in execution the Laws and orders of thoſe whom they ſerv, yet they have not been unwilling but very ready to admit to conſideration, and debate, the merit of the work it ſelf, and to hear and conſider of Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that could be offered upon any hand, by any perſons, either upon a conſcientious or prudential account; and in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to have appointed ſeveral ſolemn meetings, when not onely Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Army and perſons in publick truſt under them have been called together to adviſe, but ſeveral godly Miniſters and other private Chriſtians have been deſired to attend to ſeek the Lord together with them for direction in the work, and have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly attended, and uſed their liberties to ſpeak their opinion of it with freedom, as the Lord hath informed their judgments, and perſwaded their conſciences therein. And I do not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber any of them that have manifeſted diſſatisfaction, or offered their Reaſons againſt the work it ſelf, (ſo far as it hath hitherto been declared for, and proceeded in,) but very many both godly and judicious perſons have done it on the other hand, as to its li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitations and ſlow pace, yea it hath been the diſpoſition of thoſe in chief Authority to lean moſt towards that hand, that was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>oded with leaſt difficulties and hardſhips, upon the poor People concerned. From whence you may gather, that this Gentleman is very ſingular in his opinion, which might a little plead with him for a more charitable opinion of his different-minded friends, is to their good meanings at leaſt, though there ſhould be much reaſon of his ſide.</p>
            <p>Thus having g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ven you (to the beſt of my memory) a true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the proceedings of Authority in this matter, let us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the weight and ſtrength of thoſe Reaſons which the Diſcuſſor offers againſt the thing, and ſee what may be ſaid in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſwer thereto.</p>
            <p>And firſt, take notice from what hath been ſaid before, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:132301:9"/>
the general ſcope of the diſcourſe whereupon that Reaſon (which ſeems to be in it) chiefly hangs, is <hi>viz.</hi> ſeveral great Miſtakes, (if not worſe) For his Arguments are:</p>
            <p>Firſt, againſt a general Tranſplantation of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> whereas there is onely the Proprietors and men that have been in Arms declared to be tranſplanted, and when there ſhall as much reaſon appear for the tranſplanting the whole, as it doth now for ſuch a part, it will be then more ſeaſonable for the Diſcuſſor to offer his Reaſons againſt it: and ſuch as ſhall be then concerned in the doing thereof, to give their Reaſons for it; but at preſent there is no ſuch thing in preparation, much leſs in practice.</p>
            <p>The ſecond miſtake, is his Arguments againſt a promiſcuous Tranſplantation, without reſpect to their merit or behaviours, which (as is before aſſerted) is not ſo; for there are ſeveral per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (<hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts) who upon that account of their merit as aboveſaid, and different affection from the reſt, manifeſted to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in the late Rebellion, are wholly exempted from Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantation, either as to their eſtates or perſons, nay (as is before aſſerted) not any of them that could produce teſtimony of their good will to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt, or leaſt good office done to an <hi>Engliſh</hi> perſon in extremity upon the account of an <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> but there is a mark of favour put upon him for it, which (being admitted) the Diſcuſſors Maxime in Chriſtian Religion in <hi>pag.</hi> 6, <hi>&amp;</hi> 7. is no ways entrenched upon by the work of Tranſplanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but there is much ground to believe his ſhooting ſuch poyſoned Arrowes againſt Authority thus at the adventure, was not ſo much to heal the <hi>Iriſh</hi> wounds, as to wound and weaken the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government and Intereſt there; but innocency is the beſt Armour againſt ſuch Darts.</p>
            <p>The third Miſtake, the Diſcuſſor grounds his Diſcourſe upon, (as in <hi>pag.</hi> 7. to the 15.) is the Principle upon which the thing is done, as if Tranſplantation were principally propoſed as a Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for Murther, or avenging the Bloud ſpilt in <hi>Ireland</hi> by the Rebellion, in order to which he takes much pains to prove, that after Juſtice is done upon capital Offenders and chief Ring-leaders in a Rebellion or Maſſacre, that then the Body of the People or Commons (as he calls them) ſhould partake of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Poſition (without further troubling our ſelves with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:132301:9"/>
his proofs) may be admitted without any reflection upon the work of Tranſplantation, or the Authority impoſing or executing the ſame, for the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> (in the ſame Act of Settlement in which they make proviſion of a liberty to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant) doth there determine and appoint what the puniſhment of Murderers and chief Ring-leaders ſhould be, excepting of them therein from pardon both of Life and Eſtate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And doth therein (in <hi>pag.</hi> 2.) declare, <hi>To the end all the People of that Nation may know that it is not the intention of the Parliament to extirpate the whole Nation, but that mercy and pardon both, as to Life and Estate, ſhould be extended to all Husbandmen, Ploughmen, Laborers, Artificers, and others of the</hi> inferior <hi>ſort, in manner as is hereafter declared, &amp;c.</hi> And in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions for Tranſplanting before mentioned <hi>pag.</hi> 2. they ſay thus, <hi>And to the end all perſons in</hi> Ireland (<hi>who have right to Articles, or to any favor or mercy held forth by any the Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications in the Act of Parliament, intituled [An Act for the Settlement of</hi> Ireland]) <hi>may enjoy the benefit intended unto them and every of them respectively by the ſaid Act, It is thought fit and reſolved, That all and every the perſons aforeſaid ſhall before the first day of</hi> May 1654. <hi>remove and transplant themſelves into</hi> Connaught, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Is there in all this one word tending to ground the Tranſplantation upon Principles in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme of Puniſhments or avenging of Bloud? ſurely if a perſon in a work of this weight ſhall ſo groſly miſtake in the very Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentials and Principles upon which his Diſcourſe is founded, there is little reaſon to expect ſoundneſs and truth in things more circumſtantial and inferior. But if I ſhould proceed to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of all the reſt of his miſtakes, abſurdities, and impertinencies, as to the thing, with thoſe unjuſt and ſcandalous invectives a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Authority in his Lines, I ſhould both have tyred my ſelf in writing, and you in reading thereof to little purpoſe.</p>
            <p>But for the further clearing up the juſtice and rationality of this work, admit it in ſome degree to be done upon the account of puniſhment (which in a ſenſe may be admitted) for had they never offended they had never been liable thereto. Therefore conſider what puniſhment it was they did incurr by their offence, which will be the better done, Firſt, by conſidering the offence
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:132301:10"/>
it ſelf, which was the moſt horrid cauſleſs Rebellion, and bloudy Maſſacre that hath been heard of in theſe later Ages of the world, and the Offenders not particular perſons or parties of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation (for that had been another caſe) but the whole <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation it ſelf conſiſting of Nobility, Gentry, Clergy, and Commonalty, are all engaged as one Nation in this Quarell, to root out and wholly extirpate all <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, who had (for the moſt of them) as legal and juſt right to their Eſtates and intereſt in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as themſelves, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them poſſeſſing nothing but what they had lawfully pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, and dearly paid for, from the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and others of them poſſeſſing by right of Grant from the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> time out of minde what they did enjoy, and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equal privileges with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> if not much more, as the Diſcuſſor confeſſeth <hi>pag.</hi> 20. the Lawyers were <hi>Iriſh,</hi> the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors <hi>Iriſh,</hi> moſt of the Judges <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and the <hi>major</hi> part of the Parliament <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and in all diſputes between <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> the <hi>Iriſh</hi> were ſure of the favour (as he calls it) ſo that they were under no provocation, nor oppreſſion, under the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment at that time when the bloudy Rebells in 1641. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted that inhumane Maſſacre upon a company of poor, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed, peaceable, harmleſs people living quietly amongſt them, wherein neither Age nor Sex were ſpared, but from the old man ſtooping for age to the Babe of a ſpan long were their cruelties extended, nay the Infants in the womb were not ſecure from their mercileſs butchery, but even the women with childe were ript up, Virgins deflowred, and Wives raviſhed in the ſight of their Parents and Husbands, and then all deſtroyed together by the moſt inhuman cruelties that could be deviſed, and not onely <hi>Engliſh</hi> people but <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cattle and Houſes were deſtroyed for their being of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> kinde, and all this (as I ſaid before) without the leaſt provocation; yet this bloudy inhumane Act with all its agravations were eſpouſed by this People as a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Quarel, and a War waged thereupon, and Councels conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted for the management thereof, who were owned, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto, by the body of the People as their ſupreme legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Authority, in which rebellious practices and cruel War they perſiſted to the ruining of that flouriſhing Nation, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:132301:10"/>
of it near a waſte Wilderneſs, thereby neceſſitating <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (in the time of its own Trouble) to maintain an Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to preſerve a footing there, and at laſt forced them to ſend over and maintain a potent Army, greatly exhauſting their Treaſure and People to recover their Intereſt out of the hands of this bloudy Generation, and bring the Offenders to condign pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, who had confidence (notwithſtanding what is before mentioned) to diſpute (the ſurrender of what they had ſo boldly come by) to the utmoſt, from place to place, <hi>Ireland</hi> having coſt <hi>England</hi> more money and men to recover it, than it is or ever is like to be worth to them many a time over, and for <hi>England</hi> now at the cloſe of all to heal up this wound ſlightly, and to leave the Intereſt and People of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> at as eminent uncertainties as ever, (whereby the poſterity of this preſent Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration (if not themſelves) ſhall after a few years come to be at the mercy and diſpoſition of this bloudy People again (except a few inwalled Towns and Gariſons) if it may be by any law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and prudent means prevented) I judg thoſe who are wiſe and ingenuous of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> themſelves would acknowledg it a weakneſs, and great neglect in thoſe in whoſe hand God hath placed the power, much more all true hearted <hi>Engliſh</hi> men who are ſo much concerned therein.</p>
            <p>And therefore it remains now to prove that the work of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantation (at leaſt ſo far as it is at preſent declared and intended) i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the moſt probable means to ſecure the preſent <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ireland,</hi> and obtain one there able to ſecure it ſelf without ſuch immediate dependence upon <hi>England</hi> (as hitherto hath been) for men and money to effect the ſame.</p>
            <p>And for the better making out of this:</p>
            <p>Firſt, conſider wherein the advantage of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> above the <hi>Engliſh</hi> conſiſted at the firſt breaking out of the late horrid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, whereby the many thouſands of <hi>Engliſh</hi> People then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting in that Countrey became ſo inconſiderable either as to the preſervation of their own Lives and Eſtates, or the publick Intereſt of <hi>England</hi> there; which chiefly proceeded from their not being imbodied, or from their not cohabiting together, whereby they might have been in a capacity to imbody, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſcattered up and down the whole Nation, here and there, a few
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:132301:11"/>
families, being thereby wholly ſubjected to the mercy of the Rabble <hi>Iriſh,</hi> to the general deſtruction and ruine of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Enemy had either Army, Arms, or Ammunition, more than Skeans and Staves, whereas had thoſe <hi>Engliſh</hi> that were then in <hi>Ireland</hi> been cohabiting together in one entire Plantation, or in ſeveral Plantations, ſo they had been but entire Colonies of themſelves, and Maſters of the Countrey in which they lived, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> would hardly have had confidence to have attempted a War, much leſs a Maſſacre upon them; for then before they could have made any conſiderable Attempt upon the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> they muſt have been ſomewhat formidable themſelves, which they could hardly have attained unto without diſcovering their Plot, and there by loſing their Deſign; but in caſe they could have ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected the raiſing a formidable force before they had been diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, yet it would have been a difficult buſineſs for them to have fallen upon all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantations at once, or to have ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized any one of them more than one quarter upon which they firſt fell, from whence the whole Plantation would receive the Alarm, and either be in a capacity to draw together, to make pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent reſiſtance, or otherwiſe at leaſt to betake themſelves with the chief of their ſubſtance to ſuch ſtrong Holds or Gariſons as the Plantation did afford, and there to put themſelves into a poſture to defend their Countrey, and reſcue their friends and ſubſtance from their Enemies. And further upon the firſt Aſſault of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> upon any ſuch <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantation, or any part thereof, the whole <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantations with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army in all parts would forthwith receive the Alarm, and put themſelves into a poſture of defence, which in that caſe they might have done without much hazard or difficulty to their perſons, though their ſubſtance in ſome parts might have been hazarded by their quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their particular Habitations, to draw together, though not much, if their Plantation had been ſo ſettled upon the Sea-coaſts, as that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> could fall but upon the out-quarter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, they then probably might have preſerved all their lives, ſtock and portable goods by driving and bringing them within or under the ſhelter of their Gariſon or Rendezvous: as for inſtance, the Barony of <hi>Ards</hi> in the County of <hi>Down</hi> and Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> which being entirely planted by <hi>Britiſh</hi> People did preſerve
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:132301:11"/>
themſelves by keeping Guards upon their Frontiers, when all the Countrey beſides was totally ruined; and in all former Wars of <hi>Ireland</hi> the like ſecurity hath been enjoyed by the <hi>English</hi> pale in the County of <hi>Dublin</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Baronies in the County of <hi>Wexford,</hi> by the ſame means. Whereas by their promiſcuous and ſcattered inhabiting among the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who were in all places far the greater number and in moſt a hundred to one, they were even as Sheep prepared for the ſlaughter, that the very Cripples and Beggars of ſeveral of the Countreys where they lived (if they roſe againſt them) were able to deſtroy them, for they were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a capacity to reſiſt nor fly, being in the midſt of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and far from Friends; ſome having a hundred, ſome ſixty, ſome forty, few leſs than ten miles to travel through their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Countrey, where every Bridg and Paſs was beſet with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells to deſtroy them, that they were not onely without help, but hope in moſt places, having no other refuge, but to fly to the chief of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in their Countrey for ſuccour, who in ſeveral places ſet their Cow-boys and Foot-men to murder and torture them, and would ſtand by and make ſport of it themſelves; and others of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Gentry that were more civil would ſend them away with pretended Convoys, who uſually murdered them by the way, though ſome there were of the <hi>Irish</hi> Gentry (whoſe kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I hope either hath or will be rewarded both by God and man) that did really uſe their endeavours and intereſt to preſerve <hi>English</hi> lives, by whoſe means ſome few did eſcape (like <hi>Job's</hi> meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers) to bring the news of the deſtruction of the reſt of their neighbours.</p>
            <p>And if this were the condition of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> at the beginning of the Rebellion, and the chief outward cauſe of their ſad deſtruction, their promiſcuous ſcattered cohabitations among the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> then ſurely it muſt be the main duty of the Authority of <hi>England</hi> at this day, to contrive and uſe their utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to prevent the like ſad deſtruction for the future, which will hardly be provided againſt without the removing this main cauſe before mentioned. And therefore I would propoſe (as eſſential to the ſecurity of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt and People in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> inhabiting in that Nation ſhould live to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in diſtinct Plantations or Colonies, ſeparated from the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:132301:12"/>
               <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and (ſo far as the natural advantage of the Countrey, or their own ability will afford it) to maintain frontier Gariſons, upon Lines or Paſſes, for the ſecurity of every Plantation, and to admit no more <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts (that they had not eminent grounds to believe were or would be faithfull to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt) to live within them, then what they might have as viſibly at their mercy and diſpoſe when any new diſturbance ſhall ariſe, as the <hi>Iriſh</hi> had them at the breaking out of the laſt Rebellion, and it is my judgement it would not be ſafe to admit in any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantation, above the fifth part to be <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, either in the capacity of Tenants or Servants, unleſs in ſuch caſes where two Juſtices of the Peace, with two godly Miniſters of that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Plantation ſhould receive ſatisfaction of their being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to the Proteſtant Religion, and <hi>English</hi> Civil Manners and Cuſtoms.</p>
            <p>For though the Lord hath been pleaſed ſo far to own the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> Cauſe and Intereſt in the late War, that they have been able to engage them with far leſs numbers, that one hath put ten, and ten one hundred to flight, yet in the work of ſurprizings and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected aſſaults and inroads upon the <hi>English,</hi> the <hi>Irish</hi> have been uſually more expert and vigilant, for the <hi>Irish</hi> are naturally a timorous, ſuſpicious, watchfull People; and on the other hand, the <hi>English</hi> are a confident, credulous, careleſs People, as our daily experience in <hi>Ireland</hi> teacheth us. And therefore if their numbers ſhould be near equal, that advantage which they would have of their <hi>Irish</hi> Neighbours to correſpond with them, and fall into their aſſiſtance, would much add to their encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to attempt miſchief upon the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> with or among whom they lived, though they were far leſs numbers. And if this be not admitted, that it is eſſential in order to the ſafety of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt and people, that their Plantation ſhould conſiſt of many more <hi>English</hi> than <hi>Iriſh</hi> (as above,) then there is a neceſſity (in order thereto) that ſome of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſhould be removed out of ſome parts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to make way for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantations, and if ſo, then a Plantation muſt be admitted to be eſſential in order to the ſecurity of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt and People there. So that now the Queſtion muſt be confined to the extent and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of this Tranſplantation, Whether it ſhould be total and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:132301:12"/>
univerſal or a partial Tranſplantation? And if but a part, What part? or Which part?</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, as to the manner; Whether all at one time? or all to one place? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To the firſt I anſwer, that ſo far as the Diſcuſſor or my ſelf is able to judg, who are but private men, and not acquainted with the myſteries and ſecrets of State, the buſineſs of a total and univerſal Tranſplantation is out of Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion (as was ſaid before) All publick Papers relating to Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantation, confining that work to Proprietors and men in Arms, and therefore that I may not (as the Diſcuſſor hath done his) ſpend my pains in beating the air, I ſhall onely ſpeak to that part of this firſt Queſtion, which is at preſent in Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> What part that is? and How many, and what ſort of perſons are fit to be tranſplanted.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as to the number that is required to remove or tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant, I judg a leſs number than what is intended and appointed is not ſafe, if ſo little, for the Proprietors and intereſſed perſons in Lands, with all relating to them, (required to remove with them) cannot be rationally judged near the twentieth part of the People of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the Lands of <hi>Ireland</hi> were moſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in the hands of the Noblemen and chief Gentry, who are for the moſt part excepted perſons for Life and Eſtate, or under Baniſhment by the Act of Settlement, the remaining part being very inconſiderable for number. And for perſons that have been in Arms (though there be too many of them yet in <hi>Ireland</hi>) yet much the greater part of them are tranſported into forreign Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo that though it be hard to determine the number of theſe two ſorts of perſons, yet any man that knows the ſtate of <hi>Ireland</hi> muſt acknowledg they are probably ſo inconſiderable that they will not be miſſed or diſcerned as to their numbers in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys from whence they remove, farther than one friend may want another; and for ſuch of their friends, Tenants and Servants, (not within the Rules) who will voluntarily go with them, the uſing force to ſtay the later would be much more hard than the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving the former, ſo that as to the numbers (doubtleſs if any at all) it is not rational to think of leſs than theſe two ſorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons will amount unto.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, as to the perſons themſelves, Why theſe two
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:132301:13"/>
ſorts of perſons rather than others? I anſwer, firſt, for the men in Arms, I judg there is not much ſcruple that this one Reaſon, if there were no more might ſerve, That they have had their hands embrued in the bloud of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> in the late in humane Rebellion of <hi>Ireland,</hi> where the barbarouſneſs and inhumanities that were uſually exerciſed in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army hath ſo much enured them to Treachery and Cruelties, that they are much unfitted for living in any humane ſociety, much more with the <hi>English,</hi> againſt whom they are ſo much exaſperated; And beſides, many of them have a very great intereſt in and influence on the People among whom they reſide, that next unto the Prieſt and Land-lord the Souldier is eſteemed; and therefore the ſame Reaſons that may be given for the removing the Prieſt and the Land-lord will reach the Souldier, beſides their extraordinary fittedneſs above others, to carry on, and much more to execute any treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Deſign againſt the <hi>English,</hi> they having not onely attained to much more hardneſs and boldneſs, than the reſt of the Natives, through uſe and cuſtom, but are withall much more skilfull in the Tory War than the reſt are, being generally good Guides in the Bogs and Mountains, and experienced where and when to take their advantages to do miſchief.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection.</hi> But will it not be more dangerous, conſidering they are a People ſo able to do harm in a way of War, to gather them all into one place?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Unto ſuch as are not acquainted with the way of the <hi>Irish</hi> War, and wherein their ſtrength lies, it might ſeem ſo, but (as the Diſcuſſor acknowledgeth in <hi>pag.</hi> 25.) the <hi>English</hi> Souldiers are more afraid of Tories then Armies, and Woods and Boggs than Camps, where it will be harder to finde them than to vanquiſh them; and therefore there is nothing more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable as to the peace of <hi>Ireland</hi> than to have all perſons therein, of rebellious Principles and active ſpirits, either baniſhed or otherwiſe confined to one or ſome few places, that they may know where to provide againſt them, and keep a watch over them, which will not onely tend much to the peace of thoſe parts from whence they are removed, but alſo enable <hi>England</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their intereſt in <hi>Ireland,</hi> upon much leſs charge, for ten or twenty of theſe perſons turning Tories in thoſe parts where they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:132301:13"/>
are acquainted, ſhall require as much force to attend them, and preſerve the Countrey from them, as twenty times their number ſhall do, when confined to a little Circuit, that while we leave them in a capacity to be skulking Tories, we play our Game in <hi>Iriſh</hi> with them (wherein lies their excellency and skill) but bringing them into a body, confining them unto ſmall Circuits together, (that if they will be Torying they may be Torying up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one another, or otherwiſe if they have a minde to try their ſtrength, they may be forced to imbody) you are in <hi>English</hi> with them, wherein upon account of men you have the advantage much of them, as experience teacheth.</p>
            <p>But, ſaith the Diſcuſſor, this is the way to have Tories, to tranſplant the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> againſt which ſaith he <hi>pag.</hi> 27. they have ('tis ſtrange) as great a reſentment as againſt loſs of Eſtate, yea even againſt Death it ſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He might have left out his <hi>Parentheſis</hi> ('tis ſtrange) for it is not ſtrange they ſhould, eſpecially ſuch as are moſt intelligent and foreſeeing among them, and conſider and eſteem their rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal intereſt, for they diſcern well that the buſineſs of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantation doth more lay the Ax to the root of the Tree of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ure hopes of recovering their loſt Ground, as to that, then the whole fourteen years War hath done without it. And therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> there were no more Arguments to prove the great concernment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>f it, as to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt, the <hi>Irish</hi> great diſlike of it were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>fficient. For it cannot be a perſonal or particular ſuffering that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo much affect them therein. For one hundred pound <hi>per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>um</hi> in <hi>Connaught</hi> is as good as a hundred <hi>per annum</hi> in <hi>Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> but it is the national intereſt more than their particulars that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y ſee in danger thereby, added to that their unwillingneſs to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>it the Poſſeſſion of their ancient Inheritances, and to be ſettled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>on other mens Land in <hi>Connaught,</hi> who it's like they may fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> will bid them ſuch welcome as they will bid the Souldiers and adventures upon their Lands, ſuch nicities as theſe are, added to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> main buſineſs, may trouble them; but as to the particular <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſiſtence and livelihood, they do believe without doubt they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſhall live as comfortably and plentifull in <hi>Connaught,</hi> elſewhere in <hi>Ireland,</hi> after they are ſettled.</p>
            <p>But how if they will not go but turn Tories? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:132301:14"/>Truly, if I were convinced there were impoſſibilities or deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate hazards attending them, as to their being, or probable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable beings, I ſhould be loth to have a hand in forcing them; but if it be their dramm of rebellious bloud or fit of ſullenneſs, (which the Diſcuſſor propheſies of in <hi>pag.</hi> 25.) that alone is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with ſufficient Arguments to adviſe, it may be put to the trial, and that ſpeedily, before any more of the Army is disband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for if the buſineſs of Tranſplantation will be a ſufficient quarrel to engage them in a War again ſo ſoon, they will not long want matter of equal weight with that to pick a quarrel with us, and it's like when they may be better and we worſe prepared; for if <hi>Ireland</hi> be not Tranſplantation-proof at preſent, there is little ground to judg it will be long a quiet Habitation for the <hi>English;</hi> and therefore (though a War is to be avoided, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, by all good and ſafe means, yet) if they have a minde to it, better now than afterwards; and therefore there is much more danger not to do it, than to do it upon that account.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi> But though there may ſeem to be ſome reaſon for the tranſplanting the Souldiers, What reaſon is there the Land-lord, (or as they are called the Proprietors in Lands) ſhould be tranſplanted more than the Tenant, <hi>qua</hi> Land-lord or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The being a Land-lord or Proprietor ſingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as ſuch, is no fault, neither is there any proceedings in the buſineſs of Tranſplantation can give reaſon for any diſ-inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſed ingenuous perſons to conclude, any man ſo ſuffers, for then all <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts being Land-lords or Proprietors ſhould have been tranſplanted of courſe, without diſtinction, and if that were intended, of what uſe is all that care and pains that hath been taken to diſcriminate, as is before mentioned. Therefore no perſon is (by the Act and Inſtructions of Parliament for Tranſplantation, or any Order ſince made in <hi>Ireland</hi> in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of them) to be tranſplanted, but ſuch who are within ſome of the Qualifications therein mentioned, and do challenge an Intereſt and Propriety in ſuch part of their Lands as that Act gives them thereby, by which challenge they do give Judgment againſt themſelves, by the tenor of that Act of Settlement, that they have lived in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſince the beginning of the War and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:132301:14"/>
have not manifeſted their conſtant good affection to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England,</hi> during that time, for which they have forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all that intereſt, any ſuch of them had in Lands in <hi>Ireland</hi> (in the judgment of the Parliament declared in that Act) and as it was in the power of the Parliament to appoint what part of their Eſtates ſo forfeited they ſhould enjoy (as an Act of Grace from them) ſo was it equally in their power, to aſſign what place in <hi>Ireland</hi> they ſhould have ſuch part of their forfeited Eſtates ſet out unto them in, where it might moſt conſiſt with the good Settlement, and preſervation of the <hi>English</hi> intereſt there. And for ſuch Proprietors of Lands in <hi>Ireland</hi> as will put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon the proof of their conſtant good affection (as I judg ſeveral will do) the Authority there will readily admit the ſame, and will be ſo far from tranſplanting ſuch (as ſhall by ſuch legal trial acquit themſelves of their ſuppoſed Delinquency againſt the State) that they will rather rejoyce there is any of that Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that have been ſo faithfull as to preſerve themſelves for fit ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of their eſpecial favour and reſpect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi> But are there not many others that are no Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, who have been equally guilty with them, and yet are not tranſplanted with them? And doth not that ſavour of partiality in the doing of juſtice?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The thing it ſelf may be granted, and yet no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality in the adminiſtration of Juſtice admitted, for it is one thing to be a reſpecter of perſons in Acts of Juſtice (whereby one perſon ſhall come to bear more than his ſhare in puniſhment, and others leſs, or to receive leſs than his right in Juſtice, and others more) and another thing to extend in Acts of Grace and Favour, (which is the preſent Caſe) to ſome more and others leſs: and therefore ſaith CHRIST, Why ſhould thine eye be evil, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe mine is good? For if the Authority might juſtly have tranſplanted the whole, the ſuſpenſion or exemption of any part doth neither wrong, eſpecially when the Reaſon and Aims that lead to the difference, bear a publick ſtamp, as in order to the better ſettlement and fare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y to the Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi> What are thoſe publick Reaſons and Aims that may direct to tranſplant the Proprietor rather than the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:132301:15"/>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt, there may be ſomething ſaid as to matter of merit, wherein the Proprietors have generally deſerved to ſuffer more than the Tenant and common Husbandman; For they have generally been in a capacity to do the <hi>Irish</hi> better ſervice, and the <hi>Englih</hi> miſchief, for next unto the Clergy and Souldiery, the Proprietors were the principal Pillars of that aſſociated con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> (before mentioned) who as a Nation or Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of People eſpouſed the Quarrel of thoſe bloudy Miſcreants that murthered the <hi>English</hi> in the firſt year of the War; and in all Communities and body of People there muſt be ſeveral mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers each one acting in his place in order to the good of the other, or elſe the whole could not ſubſiſt. And therefore <hi>Paul</hi> (uſing the ſame <hi>Simile,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.17.) ſaith, If the whole body were an eye, where were the hearing? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo I may ſay, if the whole Body of the <hi>Irish</hi> had been Souldiers or publick Miniſters, where had been their maintenance and ſupport? ſo that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors differed from the men in Arms as <hi>David's</hi> men did who ſtaid by the ſtuff, from thoſe who followed the purſuit, and had they returned in like manner with ſucceſs, they would have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from their hands an equal ſhare in the Booty; ſo it is not their having Lands is the fault, but the miſ-improving that intereſt and ability which thoſe Lands gave them, above their poor neighbours, to the greater publick damage and ſuffering of the <hi>English</hi> intereſt; For it may be as well adjudged that <hi>Jeffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> Baron, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and other of their chief Head-pieces ſuffered for being wiſe men, as to ſay upon this account, Proprietors ſuffered for being landed men; for as it is moſt probable if the perſons before mentioned had had leſs wit or ability to ſerve the <hi>Irish</hi> intereſt, they had been unhanged; ſo it may on the other hand be granted, if the Proprietors had had no Land they had not been tranſplanted; and yet the Wit of the one and the Lands of the other is not the proper cauſe of either of their ſufferings, but the abuſe of both.</p>
            <p>But beſides this Argument of the different evil merit or deſert proportioned to their d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fferent intereſt and ability, there are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral others Arguments to be offered, to juſtifie the reaſonableneſs and juſtice of the thing.</p>
            <p>As firſt, you will hereby in an ordinary way break, or at leaſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:132301:15"/>
much weaken and limit that great ſpreading Intereſt of the <hi>Iriſh, viz.</hi> their ſpreading Septs, which hath been hitherto the very ſeed-ſpots, and nurſeries of all Faction and Rebellion, and withall, the preſervers of all their old Heatheniſh wicked cuſtoms and habits, which are like the humane Jewiſh, Popiſh traditions (though generally of a more wicked nature and tendency) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended from Father to Son, and ſo rivetted unto them by the reputation of antiquity, that there is little hopes of ever reclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, while thoſe Septs continue; and therefore the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplanting the Proprietors, will remove the heads and chief of the Septs from the body: for though many, who have been in arms, will go along with them, yet not all, and likely the greateſt part will not, which the Diſcuſſor himſelf in <hi>p.</hi> 23. acknowledgeth, in theſe very words, <hi>It is evidently</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for the ſecurity of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>and the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Interest to divide the</hi> Iriſh <hi>one from the other, eſpecially the Comminalty from the Chiefs;</hi> and ſo in <hi>p.</hi> 22. to the ſame purpoſe; which thing is done by this work of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantation, which he writes all theſe invectives againſt; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions do beſt ſuit with that matter that flowes from miſtakes and prejudice, and conſiſts of falſhoods and ſlanders.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Where the Septs do not extend, yet there is generally ſuch a dependance of the Tenant upon the Land-lord, that they are as much at their beck as their menial Servants, the Land-lord not uſually receiving penny Rent, but Sheaf, Proviſion and Service for their Lands, beſides thoſe other ties they have one upon another by their Foſterings &amp; Goſſippings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are uſually as much obliging amongſt them, as their natural Relations; and the Land-lord or Proprietor as much out of policy as principle, labours to preſerve theſe things amongſt the People, as the greateſt means of their intereſt in them, and as the removing the Proprietor doth in an ordinary way remove, or at leaſt weaken the Intereſt of the ruling or leading part of them, over the common People, (whereby <hi>Ireland</hi> both as to its intereſt, ſtrength and manners, will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to much leſs than the fourth part of the former extent of that Nation,) So doth it open a door and prepare a way for all that good both to ſoul and body, which the Diſcuſſor ſeems ſo much to deſire, for the poor Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ives of that Nation, without which it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely ever to be effected by ordinary means; for hereby the whole
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:132301:16"/>
body of the poor laboring quiet People of the Nation, will be immediately under the influence, education and countenance of of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proprietor or Planter, and from under the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, awing influence of his old Land-lord or Maſter, and may thereby through Gods bleſſing upon the good endeavours of the Government, be reclaimed from all their evil Cuſtoms and lewd Courſes they are overſpread with, and embrace both the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Manners, Laws and Language of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation (in Gods time) as the greateſt outward mercy they can enjoy.</p>
            <p>Beſides the making way and giving encouragement to the Souldiers, Adventurers, and other Proteſtant Planters, to plant their Lands with <hi>English,</hi> and ſettle themſelves upon them, which not one of many would be encouraged to do, if every time when he comes to ſee his Lands, the antient <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ſhall ſalute him upon it, with a ſad ſtory of his ſufferings and hard uſage, to have his Inheritance taken from him and given to other men, nay the poſterity of that <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proprietor ſhall hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ever paſs by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> mans dwelling, without curſing of him and his Succeſſors (in their hearts) and wiſhing for time to recover their own again. And this was evident in this laſt Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, where the Rebels poſſeſt themſelves of the Engliſh mens Lands and Houſes, with all they could find upnn it, as their right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Inheritances, wrongfully diſpoſed of from their Anceſtors, though they had been out of the poſſeſſion of them for ſeveral hundreds of years; Beſides, if any <hi>Engliſh</hi> men were ſo bad na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured as they could bear their murmurings and complainings, yet few of them (after they came to diſcern their danger, and the hazard of all their coſts and improvements upon their waſt Lands) would be ſo ſtupid as to continue the hazard of their perſons and familes, and their poſterities and eſtates upon a place ſo near a neighbourhood that (upon principles) were bound to hate and contrive the ruine of him and his, while he lived there. For a little experience would convince our new Planters, if what former ages have met withall, be not ſufficient, That it is ridiculous for an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man as a private Countrey man (though he would keep none but <hi>Engliſh</hi> men about him) to expect to over-top his <hi>Iriſh</hi> neighbours of equal eſtate with himſelf, for the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etors that plants with <hi>Iriſh,</hi> ſhall (upon the ſame Lands) main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:132301:16"/>
four times the number of people to be at his beck, that the other is able to do, and yet be as rich a man at the years end as himſelf, and if he keep <hi>Iriſh</hi> about him, he is then daily at their mercy, if the leaſt diſturbance or encouragement be given, as was obſerved before.</p>
            <p>But laſtly, it will not onely be an encouragement to particular perſons and Plantations of <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but (through the bleſſing of the Lord in ſome proceſs of time) may make theſe three Provinces wholly <hi>Britiſh,</hi> and thereby enable the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to ſupport it ſelf, which hath hitherto wholly depended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>England</hi> for all ſupplies, to <hi>Englands</hi> great charge and damage; and the hazards of bringing over <hi>English</hi> men bred up in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to indure the hardſhips of War in <hi>Ireland</hi> is very great, their bodies at the firſt coming will not indure it, hardly one of ſix lives; Whereas to bring over <hi>Engliſh</hi> to plant is no ſuch danger, for they not being liable to the hardſhip of Wars but accomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves with wholſom diet and warm clothes, not one of twenty of them uſually miſcarries, ſo that hereby in ſtead of having it a grave and place of deſtruction to <hi>Engliſh</hi> men as hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereto, it might become a Nurſery and breeder of <hi>Engliſh,</hi> not onely to ſupply its own uſe, to ſerve the intereſt of <hi>England</hi> elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, if occaſion ſhould be. Nay we are not altogether with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preſidents of this work in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the wiſdom of our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors may afford us ſome countenance therein, in the former Wars and Conqueſt, the <hi>English</hi> have gained in <hi>Ireland,</hi> after which (in order to ſecure their intereſt they had obtained) they have left us ſome preſidents of Tranſplantation, as a thing they judged uſefull in order thereto, as witneſs the ſeveral Cities of <hi>Dublin, Droghedah, Waterford, Cork, Youghall, Limerick, Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, &amp;c.</hi> which have been entirely planted with <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colonies, and the preſent <hi>Irish</hi> Inhabitants we found in them are generally of an ancient <hi>English</hi> extract, though degenerated from the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and intereſt of their Anceſtors native Countrey and People.</p>
            <p>But eſpecially the <hi>English</hi> Pale were anciently inhabited and planted with <hi>English,</hi> retaining much of the ancient language to this day, beſides the <hi>English</hi> Baronies in the County of <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> both which continue in ſeveral things much different from the reſt of the <hi>Irish</hi> people, which inferior or ſmaller pieces
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:132301:17"/>
of this work may point out to us, it hath been before this judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed needful, and doubtleſs if they had then obtained the ſame oportunity and ability to Tranſplant Provinces as they had to Tranſplant Counties and Baronies, they would have made their <hi>English</hi> pale of larger extent, for, compare their oportunity and power to ours, doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leſs their Tranſplantation far exceeded what is now intended. Much more might be added upon this point, to ſhew that the preſent perſons pitched upon to be tranſplant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are the fitteſt, and that their Tranſplantation doth anſwer many publick ends, and is eſſential to the preſent and future good Settlement of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the ſecurity of the intereſt of <hi>England</hi> therein.</p>
            <p>The laſt and great Objection the Diſcuſſor makes againſt this work is the impoſſibility of it; which is a conſiderable Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection if the Gentleman had produced any reaſons to prove it. For Impoſſibilities, by wiſe men ought not to be undertaken, but making ſearch for them, I could find nothing offered to prove that, more than what may be ſuppoſed to be implyed in <hi>pag.</hi> 25. wherein he ſeems to imply thoſe two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> may have a dramm of rebellious bloud left in them, and will not go.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, the power and ſtrength of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi>
is but a Scare-Crow and a Hat upon a white ſtick, onely fit to drive Geeſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore not able to make them go.</p>
            <p>If the firſt of theſe prove true, it may imply a difficulty but not an impoſſibility, for when there were many dramms of rebellious bloud in the veins of that People, it pleaſed the Lord, who is the Subduer of Rebells, to enable the preſent Army in <hi>Ireland</hi> to be an inſtrument in his hands, to let it out, and bring them under the power of <hi>England,</hi> as at this day.</p>
            <p>And as to the ſecond part, the ſame inſtrument in the ſame hand depending upon the ſame God, for ſtrength hath no reaſon (more than their own ſinfulneſs and unworthineſs) to doubt but they may be as able to compell their obedience to this work ſo eſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntially deſirable in order to the future good and ſafety of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as they have been hitherto, to reduce them from their great ſtrength, and pride they found them in, to the condition they are now brought unto, and a little compaſſion as the Diſcuſſor
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:132301:17"/>
would ſeem to allow in the hearts of the preſent perſons in power in <hi>Ireland</hi> towards the Natives there: I hope the ſenſe of ſo ſad a Judgment as a new Rebellion muſt neceſſarily bring upon that poor People, (if God ſhould give them up to ſuch a ſpirit of ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity as to work their own deſtruction thereby) would much more affect them than any ſenſe of their own danger or the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the intereſt they ſerve, by any thing they could do againſt it more than obſtruct a preſent Settlement, and as I do believe) the Jeſuits and Prieſts in the beginning of the late Rebellion did profeſs as much affection and compaſſion towards the People of <hi>Ireland,</hi> when they inſtigated and ſtirred them up thereto, as the Diſcuſſor doth or can do in his new incitements and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements to a ſecond Rebellion, ſo am I as well ſatisfied in the cloſe of the buſineſs, if they have a minde to put it upon trial, they will have as much cauſe to bewail their unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and miſery therein, and the later ſhall deſerve as little thanks from them, as the former, in the iſſue. Which one An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer ſhall ſerve to thoſe two Objections.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection.</hi> But it may be further objected, (which ſome of the Diſcuſſors Arguments ſeem to imply) though there be a power in <hi>Ireland</hi> to compell their obedience, yet there is no poſſibility in them to obtain a ſubſiſtence in their journey, or when they come there, to ſupport themſelves and families, ſo that it is equal to them to hazard their deſtruction in diſobedience, ſeeing by obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they can but periſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> If this were the true ſtate of this Caſe, there were much in it, but let us conſider it: Is this the firſt time that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have removed from one part of a Nation to another to inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit? and is that ſo impoſſible a thing, that it doth not conſiſt with the being of ſuch as ſo do? I pray you conſider what it is to remove from one Nation to another; if that be ſo, what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of all the <hi>English</hi> that are expected from thence to plant <hi>Ireland,</hi> who I hope will be far greater numbers than the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted <hi>Iriſh,</hi> many of whom muſt march much farther by Land than moſt of them can do, beſides a hazardous, chargeable and troubleſom voyage by Sea, to which is added thoſe difficulties that attend ſtrangers in a ſtrange Countrey more than what doth a people in their own native Land; and yet I hope we have ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:132301:18"/>
experience, and ſome thouſands of living witneſſes, that it is conſiſtent with their being and well-being to, and hath proved to many (if not to moſt) for their much better being, though it is to be ſuppoſed that ſuch <hi>English</hi> as dwell on the North-Weſt ſide of the River of <hi>Thames</hi> (though many miles diſtant from it) would judg it a far leſs difficulty to remove their Habitation into <hi>Surrey</hi> or <hi>Kent,</hi> than it is to remove from <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Ireland,</hi> though the later is very poſſible and practicable, as is before minded, yet the former is as much as the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Tranſplantation extends unto. Nay, we might bring for an inſtance to prove the poſſibility of the work thoſe many thouſands of <hi>English, Dutch</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> that have tranſplanted themſelves out of thoſe Nations into the <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rican</hi> Plantations, and yet are all in being and well-being too (through Gods mercy) and therefore I argue it is no ſuch impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing, as the Diſcuſſor would ſeem to make it, to tranſplant the <hi>Irish,</hi> but it may be done with much conſiſtency to their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and well-beings, if themſelves be not acceſſary to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>Beſides, if to this be added thoſe tender regards that have been (as is before minded) to the condition, age and ſex of ſuch as are to be tranſplanted, who have not been of a ſudden hurried away without reſpect to their ſeveral conditions, but the method and timing of their remove hath had a ſpecial eye to their good and preſervation therein, in order to which they have had a full years time to diſpoſe of what they have (in the places they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from) to their beſt advantage, and withall thereby oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to provide Habitations and needfull accommodations at the places they are removed to, and another whole Summer before them farther to provide for themſelves, which ſufficiently evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences the perſons in preſent power in <hi>Ireland</hi> not to have that cruel diſpoſition in them towards the <hi>Irish,</hi> as the Diſcuſſor mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly labors to inſinuate, but much the contrary; for there are many Reaſons of State in order to publick ſafety and ſettlement, that would have called for more ſeverity in order to expedition in that work, if compaſſion and tenderneſs towards the perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned therein had not prevailed againſt them, ſo that not onely to the thing it ſelf, but as to the management and method of it, the leaſt of the former Cauſes inſtanced being attended with equal
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:132301:18"/>
and moſt of them with much greater difficulties than this, and therefore not impoſſible, but as rationally and ſafely practicable as any of the former Caſes.</p>
            <p>So that I judg there hath been nothing offered by the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſor againſt the work of Tranſplantation that bears any weight, and doth not of it ſelf fall to the ground by admitting thoſe eſſential groſs miſtakes in him before mentioned, but hath been fully anſwered, either as to publibk good ſecurity of the <hi>English</hi> inhabitants and their intereſt, or as to the poſſibility and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cableneſs of the thing, without deſtruction and ruine to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons concerned, which are the principal Heads he inſiſts upon; onely as to that concerning Religion, where he endeavoureth to hold forth that the not tranſplanting of the <hi>Irish,</hi> would no ways hazard the perverting of the <hi>English,</hi> and would be much in order to the converting of the <hi>Irish,</hi> which the Tranſplanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (ſaith he) will wholly prevent, as in <hi>pag.</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</p>
            <p>But the ſtreſs of all that's offered upon this account is laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe fore-mentioned great miſtakes, that (like the bloud in the veins of the body) that runs through the whole diſcourſe, <hi>viz.</hi> a univerſal and promiſcuous Tranſplantation, which being denied is a ſufficient anſwer, for I do not judg the Diſcuſſor can ſuppoſe that the continuing of the popiſh, ſuperſtitious Souldier and Proprietor among and over the common people will be a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eans to make way for their converſion to the Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, more than to continue their Prieſts, but is ſo evident it will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>h rather tend to the contrary, even ſhutting that door of hope, but may otherwiſe be opened to that work, that to ſpend time about arguing of it would not be to profit, and beſides require <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>re Lines than I am willing to ſwell this Paper into, it being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ch larger already than I intended it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
